Okay. Uh, 6.40, you guys.
6.40.
Uh, yeah.
Leto 6. Yeah. Good. Uh so here are nine
questions and
um this is not a class this is a neg
experiment. Okay. And this is how
Negajuna used to
teach. And this is the famous last
chapter of his most of probably the most
famous book ever written in Buddhism.
And you guys have finished it for the
last seven years. And we're gonna finish
right now in the next hour. Okay.
Yay. And it's very nagar to end the
class with questions and not with
answers. Okay. Parika, right? With we're
gonna examine yourself. So he's asking
you to answer your own questions. Okay?
So you know don't just read these
questions. Ask yourself
uh this question. Okay. And uh what does
your belief
system say about the darkness that
stretches out before the light of the
know? So the guard talks about the
present moment of awareness of light and
we live in a present moment. I I
think I like to think we are like
people. So, I go
to San Diego to uh to get cut up there
every once in a while and uh there's
these very uh expensive Bill Gates's
house is next to where I stay and uh in
fact
uh what's his
name? The body Jim Day
uh met him at the in the restaurant next
to my hotel motel. I live I stay in a
little motel in on the beach, the last
California motel on a beach. And uh so
anyway, there's these beautiful,
beautiful houses there. And
uh and imagine that you buy one of these
houses. Me and Nick and Rob, we we
checked the price. I told you it was 20
million. By the way, I'm not asking,
okay? Uh I'm very happy with my little
house in Rimrock, the capital of the
universe. Uh but
uh imagine you live in this really
beautiful house on the Delmare Beach and
the waves are coming in and it's got 20
rooms and and there's a little
closet, you know, in the front of the
house where they keep the brooms and the
mops and stuff like that. And
imagine that you buy this house and then
you go in and you stay half standing up
in the closet the whole life the rest of
your life. You never go to the bedroom.
You never walk out to the beach. You
just go in the closet and crush yourself
in there and stay there with the mobs
and the brooms. Okay, that's what we
are.
Okay, we are stuck in the present moment
in a mansion called all of time. Okay,
and we are this weird kind of animal
that cannot get out of the present
moment. We live in the closet in the
mansion. There's all of future time and
there's all of past time and in for us
it's a darkness. We don't see it. We
don't experience it. We can't
communicate with it. We live in the
present moment. So what does your belief
system and I don't mean your culture. I
don't mean what your teachers told you
at school. Okay? I'm not talking about
that. What's your personal belief about
what comes after this present moment?
Okay, we talked about the lady on the
plane who you will surely
meet. But she's darkness right now. It's
all darkness. You cannot see it
directly. You can guess, you can
imagine, but you cannot see it directly.
Okay. So according to your belief
system, what's that look like? What what
does it look like five minutes from now
or five years from now? Okay. What's it
look like to you? How do you see your
future? Uh when you look into it, what
do you see? Okay. What do you believe
about
it? There I have a lot of Chinese
friends uh who are not students of mine
and they grew up believing in faith.
They call fate. I don't know what's the
Chinese
word
m anyway
fate and and often they ask me you know
can I change my fate is it possible to
change my fate so that's a worldview
about the future okay about the future
there's a old Chinese belief that it's
All set. It's all set. You don't have
any choice. Okay? And that in that's
absolutely not the belief in in this
room. You have complete power over the
future. Okay? But examine how you feel
about the future. Examine how you feel
about what's
coming and don't stand in the closet and
refuse to think about it. Okay? Human
beings are
trained by the every culture in the
world to quietly suffer in the present
and and they don't know what's coming
next. They don't know what's coming
tomorrow. You are trained by your
culture, every world culture, you are
trained to believe uh there's not much
you can do about it. You're you're
walking into the
darkness. This this moment will become
dark.
And then you will move into the light of
the next moment. And and that's do you
believe that? Do do you think that's how
it has to be? Okay. And I'm not asking
you to think
differently. I'm just saying think about
it. Okay. If you think about it, you
will draw your own conclusions. That's
Nearuna's system. Okay. That's his last
word. His last word is no
word. What's the last thing you got to
say? to I don't know. What do you
think? Okay. Then then he says, "We're
done with the book." Okay. By the way,
there's a beautiful last verse. Okay.
Then we're close. We're getting close.
Okay. So, the future's not completely
dark. Maybe. So, you know, keep these
nine questions in your heart and think
about them sometimes. You know what?
What do you think about the darkness
beyond
now? You move through now. You move
through the light of now. What's beyond
that? What's on the other side? Okay.
Second question.
6.41.
[Music]
Um, hang on. That's wrong.
Oh, I'm sorry. The first one was the
past. I'm
sorry. Okay. The first one was the past.
The darkness of the past. The second one
is the darkness of the future. Okay. So,
your past is also dark. You think it's
gone. You think it's finished. You think
there's nothing more to do about it. Or
do you How do you feel about the past?
You
know, you had experiences as a as a
younger person, you know, you had
certain
experiences. I had, you know, I can
think of experiences I had. I someone my
sister-in-law, she's cleaning out my
stepmother's drawer desk, and she found
a nice photo of me and Veronica when she
was 16.
And I'll show it
to Don't tell my wife.
Okay, hang
on.
Al Francisco. Francisco,
right? I I hope I can find
[Music]
it. No, maybe I can't find it.
Hang
[Music]
on. Oh, it's too
much. Dang.
I don't
[Music]
know. Yeah,
but hang on. Be
patient.
Anybody? You want to find it on my
phone? It's It's in
here. It's
in. Send it to me. Okay, I'll show you
later. Uh, so I'm sorry I misstated the
first question. The first question is
what does your belief system say about
the past? If you go into the past,
okay,
what's could you go back
there? Could you go back there? Okay.
And uh do you understand what happened
in the past correctly? You know, was it
just a girl in the in the
kitchen? Okay.
Uh, could the past change
now? What's your viewpoint? How how do
you view the past? Okay. And could you
be there or are you stuck in the closet?
Okay. Can you experience the past
directly? Okay. Is is it something you
can experience? Okay. You got to ask
yourself that.
And then the second question I'm sorry
is about the future. Okay? Can you
experience the future or is it dark? Is
it something you cannot go to? Okay.
It's it's up to you. Right? Those are
the first two questions. And and it's
not
uh the guardian is not saying you should
change your opinion. He's saying what do
you think? You know, what do you really
think? And I think most of us think uh
Did you find it? Most of us think you
couldn't get back
there. Yeah.
[Music]
Somebody said uh you look like Neil
Young. And I said I was trying so hard
to look like Neil
Young. Anyway, okay. Stop. Stop.
Uh so what does your belief system say?
Just ask.
Okay. Can can you be in the
future or are you stuck in the present?
Okay. Can you visit the rest of the
mansion? Can you go out on the beach?
Could you swim in the ocean? Okay. So
what's your belief
system? Second question. How many
questions?
Nine. Okay. Good.
Uh
third, what does the belief system say
about how everything there is started?
Are you one of those big
[Music]
bangers? How did everything
start? How did everything start?
And people don't
uh I think most normal people would say
this is a foolish exercise Ga you know I
it doesn't really matter you just have
to deal with what's here right I don't
think we sit at home and worry about how
did everything start
but but to ask yourself this nine
questions is enlightening according to
najana it will enlighten
If you ask yourself these nine questions
on the
plane, ask yourself these you look at
these questions again.
Okay, you want to take a photo. Did you
get it? You got it. I don't need to show
them
again, right? It's on your
phone, right? Nobody said
no. Okay, everybody got it? Yeah. So,
number three is how did everything
start? everything in the world. How did
everything
start? And that's your tawa, that's your
viewpoint. Okay, that's the 27th and
final chapter. Okay, what do you think?
And it's just questions and it's
beautiful and that's such a great
teaching
method. I'll leave you with some
questions and uh you
decide. That's
negoti what does yours and then it
became Ben's book seriously many years
later few years after that okay
uh number
four yeah how does one thing cause
another thing okay how does one thing
cause another thing and I I'll give you
the
negous scenario Okay.
[Music]
Um, so I don't know why. By the way,
Sunum, uh, I have a, uh, I have a red
ant palace,
uh, at the front step of my retreat
cabin. I mean, big, thousands of them.
And I don't know what to do when I go in
the house. Like, I'm I try to step
between them. And uh it's kind of uh
difficult. Okay. And maybe you know
there's a way you put a welcome mat over
them and they move they'll move to the
side. Okay. Just so you know it's an old
Arizona secret because to get bit by a
red ant is an experience. Okay. Uh
so anyway,
uh somebody put a huge acorn on top of
their nest today and I was like,
"What?" You know, I have a naughty kotam
mundi hanging out around my house.
There's this kind of monkey dog that
lives around
here and uh they used to live near the
spring. There used to be 10 or 12 of
them, right?
And then they had a fight and one of
them moved out. I think he's still
running around because he put a welcome
message right
next. And I think Andrea heard him but
didn't see him. Uh right. Uh
so and he put a rattlesnake on her front
step. That was pretty cute. yesterday,
day before. Yeah. So, anyway, uh I was
looking at the walnut and I was thinking
about it and uh if it if that nut could
uh open and then uh if the ants take it
down to their house and then the nut
opens and then it comes up and the and
it makes a tree there, you know.
[Music]
Can
the can the nut and the tree exist at
the same time? Yes or no? We say no.
Right? Like the nut
uh opens and a little thing comes out
and then a tree grows. Okay.
So big
question by the time the tree is there
and by the way this was negous opening
chapters if you were here 100 seven
years ago okay the opening chapters had
this
question if the chestnut the nut if it
opens and and turns into a tree is the
nut the cause of the
tree has to be I I mean, otherwise the
tree won't grow,
right? Unless there's the nuts. Unless
the ants take the nut down and it starts
to grow and the tree grows, right? Is
the nut the cause of the
tree? Can you can one thing affect
another thing if one of them is not
there?
Right? So stay with me. Don't don't
space out. Don't say, "Oh, he's doing
one of those majika things." Okay? If
there's a nut and that becomes a tree,
right? The nut turns into the
tree. By the time the tree is there,
where's the nut? The nut is gone. And by
the time the nut is there, the tree is
gone. But the nut causes the tree,
right? So, how can something which is
not there touch something which is
there?
It's it's not it's you know I'm not
being a philosopher. I'm asking an
honest question you know uh the the
kids. So the religion department of
Princeton is so small that we have to
share a building with another with the
philosophy department and there's a line
between in the hallway and they don't go
this way and we don't go that way and
across the street is the physics
department which is planning how to melt
down the whole planet and they get
federal money. They give billions and
billions of dollars but we don't get a
single dollar and uh so anyway we have
to share this building and
sometimes one of those philosophy
undergraduates will wander into the
religion department and you're like good
morning and they're
like I'm not
sure and you're like you're a philosophy
student get out of
here the religion students at that time
are like, "Yeah,
man. Good morning." Okay.
Anyway, if you really thought about it,
you couldn't do anything because the
seed is gone by the time the tree is
there. There can be no interaction
between a cause and a result. They
cannot touch each other. By definition,
one is gone by the time the other one is
there. Okay. The whole idea you have of
how things happen in the world could be
completely
mistaken. Which means all science is
mistaken and all the systems before that
are mistaken. It's possible. Okay. It's
possible. So here's the
question. What's the big nut that made
all the trees happen? Okay. What was the
first cause? Okay. What was the first
cause? What started stuff? How did stuff
start? How did stuff start? And and
asking those questions differentiates
you from an animal. According to
Buddhism, the ability to ask those
questions makes you different from an
animal. An animals, these deer, we had a
deer uh run in front of the car on the
way here. I think he was just showing
off just we almost hit it and he ran
across the road, you know, and they
they I have deer in my house, you know,
and they they eat the pomegranates and
they're beautiful. They're very very
beautiful, but but they always have some
kind of wounds on them. They have uh
cuts and they have soores and they have
they maybe they're missing a leg and uh
all all wild animals are like that. They
they cannot think how to fix uh fix
themselves. They can't do it. If they
get caught, if if something cuts them,
if they break something, it's broken for
the rest of their life and they can't do
anything. And so when you really see a
wild animal, it's kind of sad uh because
they cannot think how to fix it. They
they they don't have the ability to say,
you know, uh if I put a band-aid and I
put some cream on this, I you know, they
will walk around with an open hole in
their body and they don't know how to do
anything about it and they get used to
it. The weird thing is they seem okay.
They they're like, "Ah, it's okay. Yeah,
I got a hole in me, you know, but that's
the way it is." Are you like
that? Like, what causes things? What
really causes things? Could you fix it?
Are we like
animals? You know, do we walk around
with big wounds on our body and we just
never figured it out? Okay. What do you
think is how does one thing affect that?
How does a nut how does a seed cause a
plant? Cuz it's impossible. It's not
possible. Okay. Did you ever ask the
question? The guardian is like you're
and you're like the guardian give me the
answer. I'm used to going to Buddhism
class and they give me all the answers
and I ignore them. Uh but do you have
any answers? And he's like nope. You
figure it out. Okay. I like it. I I'm
really attracted to it. Okay.
All right. Uh, next one,
Francisco. What does your belief system,
And by the way, it doesn't mean what
your parents told you, and it doesn't
mean what your sixth grade teacher told
you. It means what do you think? What do
you really
think? How's it all going to end? The
universe, not your life. Or maybe it's
the same thing. I don't
know. How's it all going to end? What's
it What's it look like? What's it going
to look like when everything
finishes? Okay. What's it going to look
like? Right. And by the way,
uh I think all of us, we feel uh guilty
that we don't meditate
enough. And then when you finally get on
a roll, I've been on a roll. I'm up to
29 minutes. What's that mean?
weeks. Okay. Grandpa's suggestion is
start with 10 minutes. Always start back
with 10 minutes. When your meditation
practice
collapses, start back with 10 minutes.
Add one minute every
Sunday. Then you can tell my my inside
timer says 29. And I I showed it off to
my wife. I said, "Look, 29." She's like,
"19 weeks you kept your meditation every
day?" I'm like, "Yeah." Okay. So we we
feel
uh we feel like we need to meditate and
we don't really know what to meditate
about. If you want something to meditate
about, learn these nine. You can go like
this. Write them
down, you know, and then when you
meditate, it's
like you can peek. Okay. You want to try
like this?
What does the belief system say about
the end of the
universe? Okay, like I'm not asking you
to memorize nine things. Truly, you
know, it's okay, Pete. Look at the next
item on the You want to do serious
meditation or you want to watch your
breath for the rest of your life, you
know? But I mean, watch your breath
first and then meditate, okay? And then
uh here's a meditation you can do for
the
next I I usually do one for about six
weeks or something like that. For the
next six
weeks you can use this list of nine
things. By the way I have all nine on
one slide at the end but I won't tell
you that otherwise you won't take a
picture. Okay. So that's number five.
How's the universe going to end? Okay.
And if you worry about these nine
things, you will come to some answers.
Okay? And and you will realize that
everything you know is not very
important. It's these nine things that
are important.
Okay? If you don't ask these questions,
you're an animal who's getting hurt and
you you don't know what to do and you
walk around with it. Okay? You're just
walking around with it.
Okay? And that's a terrible thing. It's
a terrible thing to see a beautiful
dough with three fonts and she's got
this big hole in her side and she she
doesn't know how to do anything. You can
go out and say, "Stand still. I'll put a
band-aid on it." And she's like,
"Even rirok deers will run away
eventually." First they're
like, "You got any food?" All right.
Number six.
What does your belief system say about
the smaller endings of things? Not the
universe.
Okay? Like people or organizations or
relationships. Okay?
All people will
die. All countries will die. All cities
will
die. All
ACIs, all five houses will become
zero. Okay? that the day you make the
five
houses, you know, you're starting
something which will die. Okay? And and
by the way, there's a skill to that of
not getting depressed and not giving up
before you, you know, are you going to
start the five houses? Yes. You know,
will they end? Yes. That's not a
problem. Somebody has to we have to do
it, you know. We have to we have to
start the fire houses.
They teach us how to stop things from
ending, but they will end. Okay? And and
that's a very powerful thing in
Buddhism. The Buddha, the day he gets
enlightened, he says, "Hey, by the way,
I'm going to
die." That's that's so honest. You know,
there's so few presidents when they get
elected president, they say, you know,
someday I'll be an old guy who can't
remember how to finish a sentence, you
know, and uh it's it's refreshing to
meet an honest person. Okay. All right.
But what does you do? You really believe
your country is going to last forever?
Do you really believe your body is going
to last forever? Do you really believe
your family is going to last forever? Do
you really believe you'll be able to see
your wife and children
later? No. You go by
yourself. So, it's it's not to be
depressed and it's not to get divorced.
It's
to it's to know what the hell's really
going on and then love love other
people. Then you can really love them.
Okay. All right. Uh number seven.
I like this one. Yeah. Is there any
justice in the universe? What's your
viewpoint? You know, will good people
get their reward eventually? Will bad
people get their punishment
eventually? You know, is there
something is there a rule in the
universe that good people succeed and
bad people fail? Is there such a thing,
you know, or can you
just can you just take other people's
countries and kill their people without
anything happening to you? You know, how
does it work? You know, if you're just
bigger and stronger and more violent
than than the country next to you, can
you take it? You know, or or or is there
some kind of you can say God or is there
any is there any rule karma? Is there
anybody watching and saying, you
know, I I I when I was in
uh I don't know, I was 20some years old
and I was teaching a kids class in the
Mongolian community where I lived in New
Jersey. And uh I taught that class for
15 years to clean uh a bad karma I made
in in college. I had an abortion with a
woman. So I wanted to clean that karma.
So I asked my teacher what to do. He
said, "Teach a kids class." So I taught
a kids class. I said, "How long I have
to teach the kids class?" He's like,
"Until the karma finished." Then I'm
like, "How long's that?" He
said, "So I started and it it went for
15 years, you know, and uh it was fun.
One of them came here uh last year. He's
50some. He was the baby of the group, by
the way." And uh now he's a famous rock
and roll guy. Anyway, so
uh one one day just to have the kids
have something to do, I said, "Let's do
a oral history project of of your
people. They are Mongolian, you know,
they they came from Mongolia in the 13th
century and they took over parts of
Russia and then they uh in World War II
they escaped the Germans and they
because they were being put in the
concentration camps be the same as
Jewish people because they were
Asian and some of them escaped. the
toughest, craziest ones jumped over the
fence and they came to my town, like 400
of them. They're the roughest, toughest,
craziest of all the
Mongolians. And uh so, you know, I said,
"Let's do a oral
history project with the kids." And we
got cooperation from the local school.
And they said, "Okay, do it. We'll give
credit to the kids." And and then we
went to all the grandmas and we asked
them, tell us what you remember when you
were a kid. And we wrote a nice history
of the of the Mongol comic
Kic Mongol and uh it was a it's a
beautiful piece of work. Why am I
talking about that? We studied the
history of Genghask Khan and uh when he
was a kid
uh maybe Ezra's age, I don't know. He he
uh his his father was invited the family
was invited to dinner by the neighbors
and the neighbors uh wanted his
horses. So the neighbors poisoned the
food and uh his father was killed uh by
the poison and you know the the son and
the mom escaped. They ran away into the
forest and they lived in the forest for
years like wild animals. You know they
learned to live like a wild animal.
That's why Genghaskhan was so hard
hardened that he could take over the
world and he took over the whole world
at that time all the way to Russia. He
killed 400,000 Austrian troops in one
day. You know, you should be speaking
Mongolian. That's another
story. Why am I talking about that?
Imagine a
world where, you know, if I like Rob's
watch, I try to kill him before the
class is over. And there's no uh what do
you call it? There's no social rule
against it, you know. If there's not if
you can figure out a way to kill him
before the end of class, you can have
his watch, you know. So, I'm like, hm.
Hi Rob, what's up? You know what's that
thing over there? You know, and then you
know, imagine a
society where uh we all live like
Genghaskhan's neighbor, you know, and
maybe I'll just invite Rob to breakfast
after
class and uh I'll poison him and then
I'll get his watch. Okay. And why not?
What prevents you? What holds you back?
Why don't you do that? You know, why do
you so nice to the people next to you
right now? Why aren't you like biting
each other trying to get the blood or
something? You know
what what's keeping you back, you know?
So, so all all almost all I guess you
cannot have a society unless you have
some kind of
hesitation to to hurt another person,
you know.
And then there's bad people. There's
people who who just attack another
country, just kill the people because
they want the land, you know. There is
people like that. There is such a thing,
you know. So what what do you say, you
know, is does the universe reward
goodness and does the
universe reward evil? You
know, is there such a thing or not? What
do you really believe? And how strong is
it in your heart? Is it strong enough to
keep you from cheating on your taxes or
something like that? Okay. All right.
Number
eight. What does your belief system say
about the world's prospects for complete
future happiness and peace? Is it even
possible? Okay. And I I don't know how
you feel about it, you know, or do you
think about it? I don't know. But you
know, are things getting
better? Is there less war? Uh is there
less
violence? Uh is there more
possibility than when you were born, how
much war was there? And now how much war
is there? And are things getting better?
Are we on
a up
upward possibility or what's what's
going to happen? You know what? Are we
getting better as a as a world? Is this
world improving? Are human beings less
violent than before? 100 million people
died in World War II. 100
million. I know 50 countries killed
each, you know, killing each other.
100,000 Japanese died in the last week
of the war after the two nuclear bombs
in Tokyo. Tokyo was firebombed after the
two nuclear
bombs and they killed an extra 100,000
people for cooked them to death, you
know, after after blowing up two cities
with nuclear bombs, you know. So, are
people getting better? Is is it getting
better? You know, what's happening?
Okay. What's your system say? How do you
feel about it? Okay. Is it even possible
that we will
change? Are things getting better in
your lifetime or not?
All right.
Uh, last question. Number nine. Number
nine. The older people
understand. Yeah. Why am I alive? What
am I supposed to do here? Okay.
And uh
and I don't know about you, I had this
when I was younger. When I was
like I remember
um 10 years old, right,
Ezra? When I was 10, I used to worry
about why I was here or what am I
supposed to
do? I don't know. Does Era Ezra ever
talk about it? I don't know. like uh why
was I brought here to this world? What
is and I had a clear idea at that age? I
lost it after that. Uh you know, I was
pretty sure I was supposed to do
something special or something. Okay. So
why why are you here? Why are you
personally here? What are you supposed
to accomplish? Is there some plan for
Gibson in this world? Or is it just
Adams from the Big Bang made Gibson and
they're
gonna, you know, fall apart after a
while and Gibson's not here? You know,
is there some reason why Gibson happened
here? Is how do you feel in your heart
deep down? Do you feel like there's
something you're supposed to do
here? Is there some reason why you're
here?
I and I think as children we feel it and
then later we I think later I don't know
I think later you you stop thinking
about it right so there's nine questions
that's the 27th chapter of naja okay uh
here's the whole
list I'm sorry it's so
small but probably you could blow it up
I guess
And that's the that's the 27th chapter.
I promised you the last
verse and I like it. Here we
go. It's 650, you
guys. 650.
Yeah, there is one who was overwhelmed
by heart
love and gave up every way of viewing
things. This enabled them to teach the
holy dharma. I bow myself down to
galma. Okay. Um, in the
Tibetan, uh, there's a kind of poetry
that starts with
Kiu like that, you know, very famous.
Uh, I'm I'm thinking of somebody K.
Okay. Like somebody who I got this
incredible love in his heart.
They have their heart in
there and they gave
up nine
views.
Okay. Uh and because of that they were
able to teach
dharma. Okay. And then then there's this
it's a poetry device. You say I'm
thinking of somebody who I I'll give you
a clue. What's the clue? They got so
much love. Okay. What else? Oh, and all
those nine viewpoints, they don't have
the
nine where they think they came
from. They know where it came from. They
see the views, the real views because
they know it came from them. They know
they know the world they are in and the
nine opinions of their world come from
them. Okay. Oh, my culture is so stupid.
They don't think about justice. People
can just poison other people. People can
try to take other people's countries and
kill them. Kill them with missiles that
they can't control. They bomb schools,
hospitals, kill
kids. You know, this the kind of world I
live in. Nine bad viewpoints. Then this
verse says, who do you think made the
viewpoints? Where did those nine
viewpoints? Why? Why do you live in a
world where you kill your neighbor? You
poison. You invite your ne the neighbor
to dinner and you poison them. Okay. All
right. Cuz we still do. We didn't
improve. Okay. Going on in several
countries right now. Okay.
So he it's here. It says he gave that
up. What's it mean? He stopped thinking
it was somebody else.
He stopped thinking someone else made up
the nine
rules. He stopped thinking that they
just happened. Okay. What your culture
believes and what you were taught in
school and what your parents said is
coming from you and you can fix it.
Okay? If it wasn't coming from you,
you're in big trouble. If it is coming
from
you, just change your seats. Okay, got
it. Okay. If if it's not coming from
you, there's no reason to have a class
and we don't need Diamond Mountain.
Okay, there's a pizza place in Wilcox
finally. Okay, Kendra Ben. Pretty good.
Okay, then we should just go there and
eat pizza. There's no reason to suffer
in these classes.
Okay, got it. But it does come from you.
All right. And because they figured that
out, they were able to teach the dharma.
Okay. And then this is this riddle
poetry. In Buddhism, we call riddle
poetry. I'm thinking someone who has got
big love. What? And they realize all the
viewpoints, nine viewpoints in their
world came from them. Okay. And because
of that, they're able to teach very
sweetly. Cool. Who are you thinking of?
Gama.
Okay. Okay. And I I it's only recently I
figured out what the hell's gama. Ga
means cow. Ga means cow. Tama means
best. And in Tibetan we call kuch. Say
kuch. Kuch means uh when you have a big
bunch of cows and there's one like what
do you call that? a a type person person
alpha there's an alpha cow there's one
cow that thinks he's the boss of all the
cows and where that cow runs the other
cows will follow and that's in Sanskrit
that's ga tama okay number one cow okay
so gama refers that's what gama means
and that's the personal name of our
Buddha okay that's the name of our
Buddha so regard
Who who would have that much love? Who
would have that much knowledge of the
nine viewpoints where they come from?
Who would teach about
it? I got it. Gautama. Okay. And I bow
down to Gautama. And you are officially
finished with the greatest Buddhist book
ever written.
What's next?
Yeah, I'm honestly I got to think about
it. Okay, I gotta think about it. So, we
finished a seven-year project today in
Kyoto. We'll finish a
14-year project
Lim and Tim's asking me, you know, what
do I put on the next poster? And I'm
like, give me a few minutes to
sing. So, let me think about it. Okay,
what's next? But we'll do something
sexy.
Uh, we don't How do you want to do this?
Do you want to wrap up? Do you want to
say goodbye to everybody or do you want
to Is that a good time for
you? It's not good luck to
finish.
Uh, let me think of a sexy verse.
Yeah.
Okay.
Ready? Your body was created by a
billion good
deeds. Every time you talk,
uh, it answers the questions of
countless beings.
Uh, you happen to know everything in the
[Music]
universe. Shock your money.